<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse of the nature and obligation of oaths wherein, satisfaction is tendered touching the non-obligation and unlawfulness of the oath called, the Solemn League and Covenant : the acknowledgement whereof, is required of us by a late act of Parliament, intituled, An act for uniformity : published as an appendix to the Peace-offering / by the same author.</title>
            <author>Stileman, John, d. 1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61516</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5552</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16314</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11929084</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11929084</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51074</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61516)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51074)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 515:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse of the nature and obligation of oaths wherein, satisfaction is tendered touching the non-obligation and unlawfulness of the oath called, the Solemn League and Covenant : the acknowledgement whereof, is required of us by a late act of Parliament, intituled, An act for uniformity : published as an appendix to the Peace-offering / by the same author.</title>
                  <author>Stileman, John, d. 1685.</author>
                  <author>Stileman, John, d. 1685. Peace offering.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 24 [i.e. 30] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E.M. for Thomas Pierrepont ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Stileman. Cf.Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.)</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Solemn League and Covenant (1643)</term>
               <term>Oaths --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51074:1"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE OF THE NATURE and OBLIGATION OF OATHS: WHEREIN, Satisfaction is tendered touching the <hi>Non-ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawfulneſs</hi> of the <hi>OATH</hi> called, The SOLEMN LEAGue and COVENANT.</p>
            <p>The Acknowledgment whereof, is required of us by a late ACT of PARLIAMENT, Intituled, An ACT for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NIFORMITY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed as an <hi>APPENDIX</hi> to the Peace-offering.</p>
            <p>By the ſame <hi>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>THOR.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Thou ſhalt ſwear the Lord liveth in Truth, Judgment, and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. 4.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Juramentum Pietatis, non debet eſſe vinculum Iniquitatis.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. M.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Pierrepont,</hi> at the Sun in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1662.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:51074:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51074:2"/>
            <head>A Diſcourſe TOUCHING THE NATURE, &amp; OBLIGATION of <hi>OATHS:</hi> TOGETHER WITH THE NON-OBLIGATION and UNLAWFULNESSE Of the OATH, called, <hi>The Solemn League and Covenant.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE earneſt deſire of my Soul for the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> engaged me to ſend forth my <hi>PEACE-OFFERING</hi> into the World, to invite to <hi>Peace,</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade to <hi>Obedience,</hi> and a juſt <hi>Conformity</hi> to the Laws under which we live; wherein it was my endeavour to ſatisfie the principal Doubts, and remove the moſt material Scruples which might hinder that <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Obedience:</hi> But there is now riſen another, which I then could not foreſee; <hi>viz.</hi> This <hi>Acknowledgment</hi> or <hi>Declaration,</hi> which we are commanded by the <hi>Act of Parliament,</hi> Entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>An Act for Uniformity,</hi> &amp;c. to make and ſubſcribe, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> A B. <hi>Do Declare, That it is not lawful upon any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence whatſoever to take Arms againſt the King, and that I do abhor that Trayterous Poſition, of taking Arms by His Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority againſt His Perſon, or against thoſe that are Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionated
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51074:3"/>by Him; And that I will conform to the Liturgy of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>as it is now eſtabliſhed: And I do Declare, That I do hold there lies no Obligation upon me, or on any other perſon, from the Oath commonly called,</hi> The So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn League and Covenant, <hi>to endeavour any change or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of Government either in Church or State; and that the ſame was in it ſelf an unlawful Oath, and impoſed upon the Subjects of this Realm, againſt the known Laws and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of this Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know it will be deemed by many a matter of extream ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> for the Parliament thus to oblige men to renounce, what, <hi>with hands lifted up to the most High God,</hi> they have ſo ſolemnly ſworn; and this, by no leſs penalty than the Forfeiture of their Places, Livings, Promotions, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently Livelihoods, and means of Subſiſtence for them and their Families. But it may be remembred that there was as great ſeverity. (yea, more bitter, becauſe illegal) uſed againſt thouſands of perſons, every way as conſcientious as any now can pretend to be, both Miniſters and others, by thoſe who impoſed the <hi>Covenant,</hi> to make them ſwear it, though becauſe of the Obligation of their former Oaths they durſt not ſubmit to ſuch a perjury. I could tell ſad Stories, to which the World is no ſtranger, of men brought before <hi>Committees,</hi> Holy, Learned, Pious, Painful Preachers, unblameable in their Lives, That when nothing could be objected againſt them for Life or Doctrine, then preſently the Cry was, <hi>Try him with the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant:</hi> And the refuſal of that, though ſo contrary to the known Laws, and their former Obligations, was the expoſing of them and their Families to Beggary and Miſery. Let us reflect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that unjuſt ſeverity then, and not think it cruel now, that we are by a lawful Authority required to renounce that which was made an Engine to ruine and deſtroy ſo many.</p>
            <p>But not to diſpute the rigour or ſeverity of the Law, let us conſider the matter enjoined,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> and ſee whether there be any thing in this <hi>Declaration,</hi> which a conſidering conſcientious Chriſtian may not readily Subſcribe unto. There are but theſe three things to be declared and acknowledged.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:51074:3"/>
            <list>
               <item>1. The <hi>Unlawfulneſs of Rebellion,</hi> or <hi>bearing Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. A readineſs <hi>to conform to the Liturgy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. The <hi>Non-Obligation and Unlawfulneſs of that Oath,</hi> called the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>1. For the firſt, No Sober Chriſtian,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> or Loyal Subject can make Scruple at it, <hi>That it is unlawful upon any pretence whatſoever, to take or bear Arms againſt the King,</hi> is a Truth ſo manifeſt and expreſs in the Scriptures, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 22.21</note> to <hi>render to Caeſar the things that are Caeſars;</hi> and<note n="(b)" place="margin">Rom. 13 1. — 8. 1 Pet. 2.13, 14</note> Cuſtom, Tribute, Fear, Honour, Subjection and Obedience to our Kings (yea, though they ſhould be as the <hi>Roman Emperours,</hi> Enemies to, and Perſecutors of the Church; that he muſt forfeit his <hi>reaſon, conſcience,</hi> yea, his <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> that ſhall queſtion it. And I hope, yea, can be almoſt confident, That even thoſe who yet ſcruple the <hi>Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Covenant,</hi> and are therefore afraid to Subſcribe that part of this <hi>Acknowledgment,</hi> do abhor, and I preſume are ready to declare, <hi>That they abhor that Trayterous Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of taking Arms by His Authority against His Perſon.</hi> &amp;c. which was but a diſtinction invented to draw in many well-meaning people into that quarrel; who being afraid to break their Allegiance to the King, were abuſed by dividing His <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Politick Capacity;</hi> and perſwaded that they fought <hi>for the King,</hi> when what they did, tended to <hi>deſtroy Him.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. For, the <hi>Conformity to the Liturgy;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> that we may both lawfully conform, and conſequently promiſe it, I refer the Reader to the Diſcourſe about this Subject in my <hi>Peace-Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. But it is the matter of the <hi>Covenant,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> and the obligation thereof, which is mainly now (if not only) the matter of Scruple, and Stumbling-Block in the way of many. That they (and very many they were) who by the Command of the <hi>Lords and Commons in Parliament,</hi> and upon the ſerious exhortation of an <hi>Aſſembly of Grave Divines,</hi> with <hi>hands lifted up to the moſt High God,</hi> have Solemnly Sworne it, and engaged themſelves to <hi>endeavour in their places with all ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51074:4"/>reallity and constancy, without reſpect of perſons</hi> to perform the Contents of it; and to <hi>ſtand by all that entred into it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all oppoſers,</hi> and that <hi>no fear, terror or perſwaſion whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever</hi> ſhould draw them from a zealous proſecuting of the ends of it; that theſe ſhould now acknowledge and declare, that <hi>neither themſelves, nor any elſe are obliged by it,</hi> and that it was <hi>an unlawful Oaeth,</hi> &amp;c. this ſticks.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Some,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> perhaps, that have been over eager and zealous in contending for, and by all imaginable Arguments urging and preſſing this <hi>Oath,</hi> or, <hi>Covenant,</hi> labouring by all wayes to draw the people into this <hi>League</hi> and Combination, may think their <hi>reputation</hi> now ſo to lie at ſtake; that ſhould they now retract or condemn that, which they have not only ſworne themſelves, but have been ſo zealous and inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to make others alſo ſwear; that high eſteem, which they now have with the people for zeal and Godlineſs, would be utterly loſt; when this very Acknowledgement would make people think, that either they did heretofore go againſt Law, Conſcience, and Piety, to promote a wicked deſign; or, now as weakly, to pleaſe men, and to ſave their worldly eſtates, are ready to do any thing, and perjuriouſly to break the bonds which they were by ſo Solemn an Oath obliged in. And the truth is, while men have their eye thus upon the empty blaſt of a vain reputation, there can be no hopes to perſwade ſuch to retract an error, much leſs to condemn, what themſelves have ſo violently promoted. But, methinks, men of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and parts, and (above all) that profeſs themſelves to be <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> ſhould know, that the eſteem and applauſe, or cenſures of men, is too ſandy a foundation to build upon; and the worſt rule to guide our actions by: and be able to teach themſelves and others, that as ſometimes to fall, and be overtaken in a ſin, was the <hi>weakneſs of fleſh;</hi> ſo to perſiſt in an error is the <hi>wickedneſs of a man;</hi> but to glory in, and labour to juſtifie an evil action, is the property rather of the <hi>Devil,</hi> than <hi>Man:</hi> and that our beſt repute, and higheſt credit with God and all good men, is, <hi>that we are more ready to repent, than we were to ſin;</hi> that we our ſelves are ready to caſt the firſt ſtone, and condemn our ſelves for what we have done amiſs;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51074:4"/>that though ſin have ſometimes overtaken us as we are men, yet upon conviction we riſe again by repentance, and through grace overtake mercy. What an happineſs would it be to the Church? What a real honour would it be to the perſons them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, if they would be as forward in returning, and as zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in informing the people of their errors, and reducing them to obedience and peace; as they have ſometimes been to ſtir them up againſt the wayes of both?</p>
            <p>But I am not ſo uncharitable as to think that all, or the noſt,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> who ſcruple this <hi>Acknowledgement,</hi> are ſuch men, or only guided by ſuch rules. Many that took this Covenant, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Miniſters that preſſed it (I verily believe) thought that they <hi>muſt</hi> and <hi>ought to do ſo</hi> (though, I fear, upon no better grounds, than St. <hi>Paul</hi> before his converſion had to perſwade him that he<note n="(c)" place="margin">Acts 26.9.</note> 
               <hi>ought to do many things contrary to the Name of Jeſus:</hi> or than thoſe had, who perſecuted the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> and<note n="(d)" place="margin">Joh. 16.2.</note> 
               <hi>thought they did God good ſervice.</hi> Howſoever) many in the ſincerity of their hearts did ſwear, many through fear entred the ſame obligation: ſome think they are ſtill obliged, though they may be convinced that they raſhly or unlawfully took that Covenant. The ſatisfaction of theſe doubring ſouls, is the deſign of this Paper.</p>
            <p>We ſhall therefore examine the matter required by this <hi>Act,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> which is a Law of undoubted Authority now upon us; and conſide, whether any men are, or can be obliged by the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> mentioned, ſo far, as that they may not ſubſcribe this <hi>Declaration,</hi> or, <hi>Acknowledgement.</hi> There are but theſe two things required to be acknowledged and declared. 1. <hi>That there lies no obligation upon any perſon by this Oath, to endeavour the Alteration of Government in Church or State.</hi> 2. <hi>That it was an unlawful Oath, and impoſed contrary to the known Laws and Liberties of this Kingdom.</hi> Both which I judge unqueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onably true, and ſhall give my reaſons, that I may do my part to remove this ſtone of ſtumbling, and Conſcience being ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in this caſe, we all may obey the Law in a just conſormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and continue with chearfulneſs and peace to ſerve God, and his Church in our generations.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:51074:5"/>
            <p>An <hi>Oath</hi> beyond all peradventure is moſt Sacred,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> and hath the greateſt tie upon the ſoul; being, <hi>A Religious atteſtation of God, with an imprecation of his wrath upon us, if we break it, or abuſe his Name in it.</hi> Here we call in God for a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the truth and ſincerity of our hearts, and imprecate his vengeance upon us if we either lye, or mean not to performe what we ſo promiſe in things lawful, and in our power. Thus it is a Solemn invocation of God the ſearcher of all hearts, that he would <hi>bear witneſs</hi> to the truth, and be our <hi>Surety</hi> for what we promiſe, and puniſh him that ſwears deceitfully. So that an <hi>Oath</hi> thus ſolemnly ſworne, and religioufly taken, muſt have the ſtrongeſt obligation upon Conſcience, upon this three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold account.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. In regard of the <hi>Name</hi> invoked,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> and by which it is made. It calls in <hi>God</hi> as the <hi>Searcher of hearts</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">Rom. 1.9. 2 Cor. 1.23. &amp; 11.31. Gal. 1.20. Iſa. 65.16.</note> to atteſt it; that is, the eternal and immutable verity to confirm it: and to fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſifie here, is to make the <hi>God of Truth</hi> the Author or Patron of a <hi>Lye.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. In regard of the <hi>Imprecation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> and conſequently the <hi>ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance</hi> to be inflicted; man devoting himſelf to a Curſe, for a puniſhment of his Perjury; to be an <hi>Anathema,</hi> if he ſwear falſly, or willingly performe not, what by ſolemn <hi>Oath</hi> he is bound to do. For this was the form of, and the uſual impreca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Ancient Oaths,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Ruth 1.17. 1 Kings 2.23. &amp; 19.2. 1 Sam. 25.22.</note> 
                  <hi>God do ſo to me, and more al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, if,</hi> &amp;c. not expreſſing; but by an <hi>Apoſiopeſis</hi> ſuppreſſing the evil wiſhed; as committing it wholly to the judgement of God: <hi>q.d. The Lord thus and thus puniſh me, yea multiply his plagues and judgements upon me, as himſelf pleaſeth, if I intend otherwiſe than I ſay or profeſs.</hi> This was a thing which even Nature taught the very <hi>Heathens.</hi>
                  <note n="(g)" place="margin">Corn. Nep. <hi>in vita</hi> Ageſil.</note> When <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> a King of <hi>Sparta,</hi> and <hi>Tiſſaphernes</hi> General of the <hi>Perſians</hi> had made and ſworne a three moneths truce; The <hi>Spartan</hi> thought himſelf obliged to keep faith with his enemy, and to attempt no hoſtility. But the <hi>Perſian</hi> regarded it not, ſtudied War ſtill. Yet the <hi>Spartan</hi> perſiſted to <hi>keep his oath,</hi> expecting by this means advantage enough againſt the <hi>Perſian,</hi> as being confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that his <hi>Perjury</hi> would alienate the minds of men, both from him, and his deſigns; and moreover provoke the <hi>gods</hi> alſo againſt him, by whom he had ſworne.</item>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:51074:5"/>
               <item>3. In regard of the <hi>end</hi> for which the <hi>Oath</hi> was taken,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Viz. To make faith,</hi> and <hi>beget belief,</hi> to be a perfect<note n="(h)" place="margin">Heb. 6.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of a thing in doubt, and the beſt <hi>aſſurance,</hi> that what is promiſed ſhall be performed. The <hi>God of Truth</hi> is called in to witneſs; and his anger imprecated, that men may have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to believe and truſt us; and not doubt of the truth of our words, or ſincerity of our intentions. Words are made to be the interpreters of our mind, by which we can only know the intentions one of another; it is therefore as <hi>unnatural</hi> as <hi>unlawful</hi> to falſifie ones word, or<note n="(i)" place="margin">Lev. 19.11. Epheſ. 4.25.</note> 
                  <hi>tell a Lye;</hi> to uſe <hi>mental reſervations, Amphibologies,</hi> or <hi>Equivocations,</hi> which would make all Leagues and Contracts of no aſſurance. <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Falſehood</hi> are parts of <hi>juſtice</hi> and <hi>injuſtice,</hi> which have rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to our Neighbour <hi>ad extra,</hi> and are therefore not to be eſtimated according to what <hi>lieth hid within, in the mind;</hi> but according to what <hi>flowes from the tongue in known and intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble words.</hi> The end of <hi>words</hi> is to teſtifie the hidden truth of the <hi>heart.</hi> But when an <hi>Oath</hi> ſhall be added to theſe words, and the <hi>Eternal <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erity</hi> called in to witneſs that our tongues do faithfully declare our minds, this is added to beget a firmer belief, and to falſifie here is a greater ſin: a Truth which all men, even the Heathen have received as Sacred.<note n="*" place="margin">Vid. <hi>Simſ.</hi> Chron. Cath. in <hi>Perfic.</hi> p 115.</note> When <hi>Lacrates</hi> the <hi>Theban</hi> Captain beſieged <hi>Peluſium</hi> in the behalf of the <hi>Perſians;</hi> at laſt it yielded upon terms; and <hi>Oath</hi> was given that the <hi>Greeks</hi> yielding the Caſtle, ſhould go out ſafe with all their goods, and be conveyed to their Countries. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on confidence of this <hi>faith</hi> given by <hi>Oath,</hi> they yield, but the <hi>Perſian</hi> Souldiers under <hi>Bagoas,</hi> the Kings Lieutenant coming in, contrary to the <hi>Oath</hi> fall to Pillaging the poor <hi>Greeks,</hi> they now can do nothing but bewail their miſery, complain of the Perjury, calling on the gods to puniſh it. But <hi>Lacrates,</hi> who had made the terms, and given his <hi>Oath,</hi> in zeal to his Oath, falls upon the <hi>Perſians</hi> for whom he fought; and protects the <hi>Greeks,</hi> to whom he had ſworne. The <hi>Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> accuſe <hi>Lacrates</hi> as taking part with the <hi>Greeks</hi> againſt them, but the King (who was then <hi>Ochus,</hi> even the ſame who was <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> the husband of <hi>Heſter</hi>) hearing the cauſe, juſtified <hi>Lacrates,</hi> condemned his own Lieutenant,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51074:6"/>
                  <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as;</hi> determined that thoſe <hi>Perſians</hi> were juſtly ſerved; and ordered further puniſhment ſhould be taken upon them, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <hi>brake the Oath</hi> and pillaged the <hi>Greeks.</hi> So Sacred a thing did that Barbarous King eſteem an <hi>Oath</hi> to be.</item>
            </list>
            <p>There is no doubt then,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> but there is an high obligation by an <hi>Oath</hi> upon the ſoul. But yet not ſuch an obligation in <hi>eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Oath,</hi> as to bind the Sweater to an actual performance of it. For it is no difficult matter to give inſtances of ſome <hi>Oaths</hi> that have been wickedly entred into, and more wickedly kept. And therefore we muſt conſider as the nature, ſo the ſeveral qualities of <hi>Oaths,</hi> that we may better be able to judge when and how far they bind.</p>
            <p>As to an <hi>Oath</hi> then,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> that we may neither ſin in the taking, nor in the keeping of it, God hath given us this expreſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,<note n="(k)" place="margin">Exod. 20.7.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the Name of the Lord thy God in vain,</hi> &amp;c. And for the preſerving this Name of God from all prophanation, which is much prophaned by <hi>raſh, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate, irreligious Oaths;</hi> by <hi>Perjury,</hi> and by <hi>not perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming our Oaths to the Lord;</hi> yea, and by <hi>doing,</hi> upon pretence of an Oath, <hi>what we ought neither to ſwear, nor do:</hi> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet hath ſet this threefold boundary about all our Oaths.<note n="(l)" place="margin">Jer. 4.2.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt ſwear — in Truth, Judgement, and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: (i. e.)</hi> Truly, conſiderately, and juſtly. So that to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very lawful <hi>Oath,</hi> there are theſe three things prerequiſite.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Truth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>16.</hi>
                  </note> That God be not invoked to a lye. Here the Law is,<note n="(m)" place="margin">Lev. 19.12</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſwear by my Name falſly,</hi> a crime<note n="(n)" place="margin">Iſa. 48.1. Jer 5 2.</note> charged upon <hi>Iſrael</hi> as their ſin. For this is to make the <hi>Eternal Truth</hi> witneſs to a <hi>Lye,</hi> and lay an impuration up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God, to be (as<note n="(o)" place="margin">Joh. 8.44.</note> the Devil) <hi>the Father</hi> and Factor <hi>of Lyes.</hi> Here then we are obliged, to ſweat to nothing, but what is <hi>True, viz.</hi> to aſſert nothing but Truth: and our hearts and words going together, that we really endeavour to make good what we have ſworne.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>Judgement.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> That we ſwear not <hi>raſhly</hi> or <hi>inconſiderately,</hi> but ſeriouſly conſider what we ſwear, and whoſe Name we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke: that an Oath may be taken with the greateſt care, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, and deliberation. Leſt the Sacred Name of God be prophaned by idle, light, and cuſtomary <hi>Oaths;</hi> or our ſelves
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51074:6"/>irreparably ſnared by our inconſiderateneſſe, as <hi>Joſhua</hi> and <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> were<note n="(p)" place="margin">Joſh. 9.15. — 25.</note> by ſwearing to the <hi>Gibeonites.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſſe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note> To do nothing but what is juſt and honeſt, leſt we make God the countenancer of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe, and call in the <hi>moſt Holy</hi> to patronize impiety or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice. Such an <hi>unjuſt Oath</hi> was that of<note n="(q)" place="margin">1 Sam. 14.39.44.45.</note> 
                  <hi>Saul,</hi> whereby he would have killed his ſon:<note n="(r)" place="margin">1 Sam. 25.22. —</note> of <hi>David,</hi> to deſtroy <hi>Nabals</hi> houſe: of the<note n="(s)" place="margin">Acts 23.12</note> 
                  <hi>fews</hi> to murder <hi>Paul.</hi> The cauſe, ground and matter of the <hi>Oath</hi> muſt be <hi>juſt, honeſt, laewful, poſſible,</hi> and <hi>conſonant to the revealed will of God.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe three conditions muſt have place in all ſorts of <hi>Oaths,</hi> which are fully compriſed under theſe two general heads.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. An <hi>Aſſertory Oath,</hi> which is nothing elſe but a <hi>Depoſition:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>19.</hi>
                  </note> that, of which the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, when he ſaith, that<note n="(t)" place="margin">Heb. 6.16.</note> 
                  <hi>an Oath for confirmation is the end of ſtrifes.</hi> Which muſt be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as without which many controverſies, queſtions, and ſuits of Law were indeterminable. The uſe of this <hi>Oath</hi> is, when we are called, to witneſſe and declare what we know of a thing <hi>paſt</hi> or <hi>preſent,</hi> the truth whereof we are bound then by <hi>Oath</hi> to declare, ſo far as we know. In this the three forementioned conditions have place, thus. 1. <hi>Truth,</hi> that we affirm or deny nothing, but what we know infallibly, evidently, and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: or, if the thing be doubtful, that we affirm or deny it, but as ſuch, and venture no farther than a probability, <hi>viz.</hi> that there be perfect truth in our words. 2. <hi>Judgment, viz.</hi> 1. That we remember it is the <hi>Oath of God,</hi> an holy thing, and not to be made profane or common; nor taken, but when by a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful authority we are called unto it. 2. In great, and ſerious, and weighty cauſes, or matters of moment, to which only it is fit to call down (as by <hi>Oath</hi> we do) the <hi>great God</hi> from heaven to be a Witneſſe and Judge. <hi>Nec Deus interſit, niſi dignus vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicè nodus inciderit</hi> — 3. Not out of any levity, love, hatred, or any paſſion or perturbation of mind; but a juſt and lawful neceſſity: when no other way remains to prove the truth, or put an end to controverſies. 3. <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſſe.</hi> When we are juſtly called to take it, and when we ſwear, we ſwear from an honeſt heart. Here <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> is much what the ſame. Theſe <hi>Oaths</hi> refering only to the time <hi>paſt</hi> or
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51074:7"/>
                  <hi>preſent,</hi> the <hi>Truth</hi> in them is but <hi>ſingle;</hi> relating only to the time preſent, or the <hi>Act of ſwearing, viz.</hi> that this is Truth, which we now depoſe. The difficulties about theſe <hi>Oaths</hi> therefore are not many, nor very implicate, becauſe thus their whole truths are immediately fulfilled in the preſent act, and a farther obligation theſe have not. But the moſt difficulty is concerning another ſort of Oaths, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Promiſsory Oaths.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> Which have reſpect to the <hi>time to come,</hi> and lay an obligation for the future. For by theſe we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage our ſelves to do ſomething hereafter. Such was that<note n="(v)" place="margin">1 Kings 1.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> that <hi>Solomon ſhould reign after him.</hi> This, when made to <hi>God,</hi> is called a <hi>Vow;</hi> when to <hi>man,</hi> an <hi>Oath.</hi> The Obligation in both is the ſame, becauſe made in the name of God.<note n="(x)" place="margin">Pſal. 76 11</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ow and pay to the Lord,</hi> ſaith one text, and<note n="(y)" place="margin">Mat. 5.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt perform to the Lord thine Oaths,</hi> ſaith another. This alſo muſt have the ſame conditions, of,
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Truth,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>21.</hi>
                        </note> that we promiſe only, what we ſincerely mean to perform; and that we do really perform, or at leaſt endeavor our beſt and utmoſt to perform what we have ſo promiſed. So that the <hi>Truth,</hi> which in the <hi>Aſſertory Oath</hi> is onely <hi>ſingle,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the <hi>preſent,</hi> and <hi>Act of ſwearing,</hi> is in this <hi>promiſſory Oath double.</hi> 1. In regard of the <hi>preſent,</hi> that our <hi>mind</hi> and <hi>words</hi> go congruouſly together; that, as we promiſe, ſo there be a real ſincere intention to perform, and here lies on the ſoul an immediate obligation, that in the very <hi>act of ſwearing,</hi> our <hi>words be according to our intentions.</hi> 2. In reference to the <hi>ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,</hi> and <hi>time to come,</hi> that we will have our <hi>Actions</hi> go along with our <hi>words;</hi> and that by our utmoſt endeavors in all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt wayes we will labour to make our words good.</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Judgment.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>22.</hi>
                        </note> That (as in the former ſo in this) we 1. With reverence remember <hi>by whom we ſwear,</hi> the name of the <hi>great God,</hi> ſo as we enter not this <hi>Oath</hi> upon light and trivial cauſes, or, not lawfully called to it. 2. That upon mature deliberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we ſo promiſe, what we promiſe by oath, conſidering well the matter and circumſtances to which we are engaged; leſt by our inconſiderateneſſe we ſhould oblige our ſelves to a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief or inconvenience. 3. That, what we promiſe be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and in our power; leſt otherwiſe by our raſhneſſe we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51074:7"/>engaged, where by reaſon of the impoſſibility of perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance we cannot but break our Oaths. That we be not drawn either by affection, paſſion, fear or terror to promiſe that, which in out unbiaſſed thoughts we would not, or might nor do.</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſſe,</hi> that what we promiſe be juſt,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>23.</hi>
                        </note> honeſt, lawful and agreeable to the Word of God; not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to any moral precept, nor our former lawful Oaths, and not yet reſcinded obligations. So that, as 1. They ſin againſt this, who having ſworn, and being obliged to the duty of any moral precept, yet for gain, intereſt, vain reputation, &amp;c. ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve themſelves at pleaſure, and perform not their Oaths: So 2. Do they ſin alſo, who enter into Oaths and Obligations to do, what they are obliged not to do, as to <hi>lye, kill, ſteal, &amp;c.</hi> Such was the Oath of the<note n="(z)" place="margin">Acts 23.12</note> 
                        <hi>Jews</hi> to kill <hi>Paul;</hi> of<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 14 8. — 12.</note> 
                        <hi>Herod</hi> to <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>odias,</hi> both <hi>raſh,</hi> and againſt <hi>judgment</hi> in the Act, ſwearing to give her <hi>any requeſt,</hi> not conſidering how unjuſt, or unequal a thing ſhe might ask; and <hi>unjuſt</hi> and <hi>wicked</hi> in the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the <hi>Murder</hi> of an <hi>innocent Man,</hi> and an holy <hi>Prophet of God.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Promiſſory Oaths</hi> only are the matter of our preſent conſideration,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> as thoſe only which have an obligation upon us for the future. And becauſe the <hi>Matter of this Oath,</hi> which is in the future to be fulfilled, is naturally ſubject to change whether we will or no, the <hi>Obligation</hi> therefore muſt needs be <hi>mutable,</hi> and <hi>ſeparable from the Oath.</hi> It is in our pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to make the <hi>first</hi> truth good, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>our minds and intentions ſhall go along with our words;</hi> but the <hi>ſecond</hi> is not alwayes in our power, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>our Deeds and Actions ſhall exactly anſwer either our words or intentions.</hi> He is forſworn, who intends not what by Oath he promiſeth; but he is not alwayes forſworn, who effects not what he hath ſo ſworn.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore conſider the Caſes,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> how far theſe <hi>Oaths</hi> oblige; and when, or where the Obligation ceaſeth; for I doubt not, but there is an unqueſtionable Truth in both theſe Propoſitions.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That though a <hi>lawful Oath</hi> generally obligeth, yet there are ſome Caſes and Times where it obligeth not: And,</item>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:51074:8"/>
               <item>2. That there is ſome kind of <hi>unlawful Oath</hi> that ſtill ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligeth; ſo that on the one ſide, <hi>Sometimes an Oath may be lawfully ſworn, yet afterwards unlawfully kept;</hi> on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, it may be <hi>unlawfully ſworn, yet may be lawfully kept, and would be unlawfully broken.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Therefore as to the <hi>lawfulneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> or <hi>unlawfulneſs of Oaths,</hi> I muſt premiſe this diſtinction, which is but neceſſary for the better underſtanding, wherein they are <hi>lawful</hi> or <hi>unlawful,</hi> and we may be able to give a clearer judgment of the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Oaths</hi> may be ſaid <hi>lawful</hi> or <hi>unlawful.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. In regard of the <hi>Impoſers</hi> or <hi>Exacters</hi> of them. They are lawful, when we are called to ſwear by a <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>lawful</hi> Authority; <hi>unlawfully</hi> impoſed, when by an <hi>uſurping</hi> and <hi>unlawful</hi> Authority.</item>
               <item>2. In regard of the <hi>Act, Manner,</hi> and <hi>Motive</hi> of <hi>ſwearing.</hi> It is <hi>lawful,</hi> when upon a <hi>lawful cell,</hi> from an <hi>honeſt heart,</hi> upon <hi>mature judgment:</hi> But not ſo, when <hi>raſh,</hi> or <hi>inconſiderate,</hi> drawn by <hi>Affection,</hi> hurried by <hi>Poſſion,</hi> driven by <hi>Fear,</hi> or extorted by <hi>Force.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. In regard of the <hi>Matter</hi> ſworn to; whether <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>honeſt,</hi> or <hi>evil</hi> and <hi>unlawful</hi> to be done. In the <hi>firſt</hi> Notion, an <hi>unlawful Oath</hi> may oblige; ſometimes in the <hi>ſecond;</hi> but never in the <hi>laſt.</hi> Theſe things will help us to judge what <hi>Oath</hi> is <hi>lawfully</hi> or <hi>unlawfully</hi> taken; and when the <hi>Obligation of a lawful Oath</hi> ceaſeth, and where it continues: And where an <hi>unlawful Oath</hi> obligeth, or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligeth not. I ſhall give you my thoughts in theſe Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>1. It is beyond all queſtion that <hi>all Oaths,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>27.</hi>
                  </note> lawfully requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to which we are called by a juſt Authority, the matter whereof is juſt, honeſt, and in our power to perform, do indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſibly oblige the conſcience, ſo long, and ſo far, as thoſe who required the Oath, will that they ſhould. This I take as ſo clear and unqueſtionable, that it needs no proof nor expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</item>
               <item>2. <hi>All Oaths,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>28.</hi>
                  </note> where the matter is juſt, or they oblige not to any diſhoneſt thing, though they are raſhly ſworn or upon ſurpriſe, though impoſed by unjuſt Powers, extorted by force,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51074:8"/>and cannot be kept but to our own inconvenience, and ſo conſequently <hi>unlawful Oaths,</hi> perhaps, <hi>ſnfully ſworn,</hi> as being contrary to that condition of ſwearing, <hi>in judgment;</hi> yet <hi>may lawfully be kept,</hi> yea, ſometimes, and in ſome caſes do oblige, and <hi>may not be broken.</hi> Such was the caſe of <hi>Pomponius</hi> the <hi>Raman Tribun.</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cic.</hi> de Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic. <hi>l. 3. ad fin. cap.</hi> de Fortitud,</note> He had ſummoned <hi>L. Manlius</hi> to appear in court to an accuſation againſt him concerning his too ſevere uſage of his ſon. The ſon <hi>T. Manlius</hi> hearing of it, went into the Chamber of the <hi>Tribune,</hi> and with his drawn ſword threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his life, if he preſently ſwore not to him to withdraw the Action againſt his Father. <hi>Pomponius</hi> through this terror took ſuch an Oath; and when the day came, declared the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the people, and according to his Oath, withdrew the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. So <hi>Religious a tie</hi> was an <hi>Oath</hi> eſteemed in thoſe dayes, though it were extorted by terror. The like may be ſaid of Oaths in caſe of ſurpriſal: ſuch was the caſe of <hi>Alexander M.</hi> The ſtory is this,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pauſan. <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ac.</hi> 2. Valer. Max. <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> The Citizens of <hi>Lampſacum</hi> had joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>Darius</hi> the <hi>Perſian</hi> againſt the <hi>Greeks: Alexander</hi> who had the command of all the <hi>Graecian</hi> forces, marcheth with fury, threatning utter deſtruction to theſe <hi>Lampſacenians;</hi> they affrighted, ſend one of their chiefeſt Citizens, one <hi>Anax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imenes</hi> to beg favour: <hi>Alexander</hi> to prevent him and his ſuit, ſwears that he wil not grant that which <hi>Anaximenes</hi> ſhould ask: <hi>Anaximenes</hi> takes advantage, and ſurpriſeth him upon his Oath, Petitions that he would deſtroy the City, demoliſh their Temples, captivate and ſell the inhabitants; thus was <hi>Alexander</hi> wittily circumvented, and the City ſaved, <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> thinking himſelf bound by his Oath not to deſtroy it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Anaximenes</hi> had ſo petitioned, whom he had ſworn to deny. Here was an <hi>Oath raſhly</hi> taken, the ſwearer <hi>ſurprized,</hi> who yet accounted himſelf obliged. Shall I adde another? a caſe which the Scripture records, it is that <hi>oath</hi> of<note n="(d)" place="margin">Joſh. 9.4-20.</note> 
                  <hi>Joſhua</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> to the <hi>Gibeonites:</hi> they by craft obtain a League, which they ſhould not have obtained, had they been known inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the Land, whom <hi>Iſrael</hi> had commiſſion to deſtroy, but they pretending a long journey, an Embaſſy from a far Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, <hi>Joſhua</hi> and the <hi>Elders of Iſrael</hi> are furprized, the <hi>League</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:51074:9"/>is made, and <hi>ſworn</hi> to, <hi>to let theſe Gibeonites</hi> live. The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, when they hear the fraud, murmure againſt the Princes, but they anſwer, <hi>We have ſworn to them by the Lord God of Iſrael, therefore we may not touch them.</hi> They knew they were (though raſhly ſworn) yet now obliged, and God did af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ſeverely<note n="(e)" place="margin">2 Sam. 21.1-10.</note> puniſh the breach of this Oath upon the houſe of <hi>Saul,</hi> who ſought to ſlay the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                        <desc>•••…</desc>
                     </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>onites</hi> contrary to this League, though it was in <hi>his zeal to the Children of Iſrael and Judah.</hi> Such Oaths then, though <hi>extorted,</hi> or <hi>unjuſtly impoſed,</hi> or <hi>raſhly taken,</hi> yet when their matter is not diſhoneſt or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, do bind, though it may be to our own damage or incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience. He that hath ſo ſworn may have reaſon to repent of his raſhneſſe, but muſt perform his Oaths, when he hath <hi>ſworn,</hi> though<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſal 15.4.</note> 
                  <hi>to his own hurt,</hi> he muſt <hi>not change.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. But there are ſome caſes wherein both a <hi>lawful oath ceaſeth to oblige;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>29.</hi>
                  </note> and an <hi>unlawful oath never did, nor can oblige to the actual performance of it.</hi> The matter of a <hi>Promiſe,</hi> and conſequently of a <hi>Promiſſory oath,</hi> is ſomething <hi>future:</hi> now what is ſuppoſed <hi>future</hi> may yet be 1. <hi>Neceſſary.</hi> 2. <hi>Imp ſſible.</hi> 3. <hi>Poſſible.</hi> The <hi>firſt</hi> is <hi>neceſſary to be perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and muſt be done;</hi> the <hi>ſecond</hi> cannot be expected, nor can there be an obligation to do, what (not only may not but) <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be done:</hi> The <hi>laſt may.</hi> But this depending ſo much upon our own or others <hi>wills;</hi> and there being alſo many <hi>contingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> which cannot be determined by our <hi>wills;</hi> our ſtate and condition here being in continual motion and change: this is that which makes the Difficulty, and is the matter of <hi>perplexing oaths,</hi> and promiſes. It muſt therefore be moſt evident, that there is <hi>no promiſe</hi> or <hi>oath,</hi> which, in theſe things whoſe futu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rition is ſubject to, and depends upon ſo many contingencies; can be ſo poſitive and abſolute; but muſt be ſuppoſed to have ſome tacit but neceſſary conditions annexed to them: by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereof a man may ſometimes <hi>not keep,</hi> and yet not be guilty of the <hi>bleach of his oath:</hi> yea, ſometimes may be obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <hi>not to keep it,</hi> for all our engagements and actions lie open to the controlments that may be made by a <hi>Law, Juſtice,</hi> the <hi>power of our Superiours,</hi> and the <hi>Rights of another third perſon.</hi> So that,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51074:9"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. There may be,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>30.</hi>
                        </note> and oft is (as the <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>ſuiſts</hi> term it) <hi>Solutio vinculi per ceſſationem materiae, &amp; mutationem fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam circa cauſam juramenti principalem.</hi> When the <hi>matter of the Oath</hi> is taken away, or ſome <hi>notable</hi> and material <hi>change</hi> made in that which was the <hi>principal cauſe of the Oath,</hi> the bond is looſed, and he that was obliged, is now free. For this muſt be ſuppoſed as the tacite condition, <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ebus ſic ſtantibus,</hi> That things ſtand and continue as they do, or that there ſtill be the ſame occaſion of doing the thing now, as there was of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, of ſwearing to do it, when the Oath was taken. And thus
<list>
                           <item>1. The <hi>Matter of the Oath</hi> ceaſeth,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>31.</hi>
                              </note> when the ſtate of things is ſo changed between the time of <hi>ſwearing</hi> and <hi>falfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> that had they been ſo then as they are now, or had we foreſeen this change and ſtate of things, the <hi>Oath</hi> would not have been required, yea ought not to have been taken at all. For inſtance,<note n="(g)" place="margin">1 Kings 1.52.</note> 
                              <hi>Solomon</hi> forgave <hi>Adonijah</hi> his offence in U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurping the Crown, on condition that <hi>wickedneſs ſhould not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards be found in him.</hi> After this comes in<note n="(h)" place="margin">1 Kings 2.20.</note> 
                              <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                                    <desc>••</desc>
                                 </gap>eba</hi> with a Petition for him, and King <hi>Solomon</hi> gives her an abſolute pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe that <hi>be will not deny her.</hi> Upon this abſolute grant ſhe goes on to ask<note n="(i)" place="margin">Ver. <hi>21.</hi>
                              </note> 
                              <hi>Abiſhag</hi> one of <hi>Davids</hi> Concubines, a <hi>wife for Adonijah:</hi> upon this <hi>Solomon</hi> notwithſtanding his former peremptory engagement to his Mother, <hi>not to deny her,</hi> not only doth not make that good; but moreover alſo takes a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Oath,<note n="(k)" place="margin">
                                 <hi>Ver.</hi> 22, 23, 24.</note> 
                              <hi>Adonijah ſhould die.</hi> Here is an evident contradiction to his former peremptory Promiſe, and yet he cannot be ſaid to break promiſe, nor had he ſworne to the promiſe, could he for this be accuſed of dealing ſalſly; becauſe in the Poſitive grant by the Promiſe, there muſt be underſtood this tacit condition, that <hi>Adonijah</hi> (according as his former pardon went) ſhould attempt nothing unlawful, which he now did, it being <hi>Treaſon</hi> for any, to attempt the <hi>Concubines of the deceaſed King,</hi> beſides the Succeſſor; for<note n="(l)" place="margin">2 Sam. 12.8 &amp; 16.21.</note> his only they were. Here was a notable alteration in the matter. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made and ſworne to <hi>Adonijah,</hi> was, as to <hi>faithful and loyal,</hi> the caſe is altered when he turns <hi>Traytour.</hi> Thus, thoſe who have ſubſcribed and ſworne to the uſe of the <hi>Liturgy</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> did ſubſcribe and ſwear to that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51074:10"/>
                              <hi>Liturgy</hi> which was eſtabliſhed, and as it was eſtabliſhed in 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
                              <hi>Elizab.</hi> but now ſeveral alterations being made in the Book, and eſtabliſhed by a Law of undoubted Authority, this is ſuch an alteration in the <hi>Matter,</hi> as frees thoſe from that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation as to that Book, when the time comes that this new one takes place, and is in force. And to this I refer this alſo,</item>
                           <item>2. A Freedom from the bond or obligation,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>32.</hi>
                              </note> when the ſame Authority, that required the Oath, gives a <hi>Relaxation,</hi> or cancels and <hi>annuls that Oath.</hi> Thus he, that fulfils not his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to him, that will not have it fulfilled, breaks not his word: The reaſon is, becauſe no man is Maſter of anothers right; neither have we a right of making others keep, what is their own property, longer than they will themſelves. To <hi>Pay a debt</hi> is alwayes the duty of the <hi>Debtour,</hi> ſo long as the <hi>Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour</hi> will have it ſo: but it is not alwayes a duty in the <hi>Creditour</hi> to receive it from the <hi>Debtour:</hi> Acceptation here is equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to Payment. If I promiſe another, and ſwear to pay him 100 <hi>l.</hi> I am bound if he will accept it; but if he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe the Debt, I am free from the Obligation. So in this caſe, if a Servant ſwear to a Maſter to ſerve him ſuch a Term of years, He is obliged, if the Maſter ſtill require it, but if the Maſter will diſcharge him ſooner, he is free, notwithſtanding his former Oath. The like reaſon there is (I conceive) in <hi>Pablick Oaths,</hi> ſuppoſe them enacted by a lawful Authority; we ſwear lawfully, and are bound ſo long as that Authority will have that in force to which we ſwore. But if the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority annul the Law, and revoke the matter, we are alſo free. As ſuppoſe I were called to ſwear, that I would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly uſe the <hi>Liturgy</hi> now eſtabliſhed, and no other, I were bound by my <hi>Oath,</hi> as well as by the <hi>Act</hi> that enjoynes it: but ſhould this be taken away hereafter by a <hi>Law,</hi> and the ſame Authority <hi>(i.e.)</hi> an <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> take away this, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire another Form, I ſhould be free of that Obligation: for the Oath ſuppoſeth the Authority ſtill requiring it. In ſuch a notable alteration we lawfully may not do, yea muſt not do (unleſs our Oath can oblige us to reſiſt a Law, which God hath bound us to obey) what we lawfully did by Oath promiſe to do.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:51074:10"/>
                     <item>2. <hi>Thoſe Oaths</hi> whereby we bound our ſelves to <hi>Impoſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>33.</hi>
                        </note> were <hi>Raſhly,</hi> and <hi>inconſiderately</hi> taken; and may not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>lawfully be broken,</hi> but indeed <hi>cannot be kept:</hi> and the very <hi>Impoſſibility of Performance</hi> makes <hi>a nullity in the Obligation.</hi> Whether the things ſworne to, are, 1. <hi>Impoſſible in Nature.</hi> As if I by Oath ſhould engage my ſelf to number the Stats, or the ſands on the Sea ſhore, or hold the Ocean in the hollow of my hand: I ſhould be ſinfully involved in the guilt of a <hi>raſh Oath;</hi> yet could not be obliged to that, which <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> have made impoſſible. Or. 2. Whether they be <hi>Moral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and <hi>in equity Impoſſible.</hi> What we ſwear, muſt be <hi>in our Power:</hi> for this alſo is ſuppoſed a tacite condition, that <hi>we have power to do that, which we ſwear to do.</hi> This, I conceive, was that which by the Law of the <hi>moſt Righteous God,</hi>
                        <note n="(m)" place="margin">Num. 30.8, 12, 14.</note> freed <hi>a Wife,</hi> or <hi>a Child</hi> from the obligation of their <hi>Oath</hi> or <hi>Vow,</hi> when the <hi>Husband</hi> or <hi>Father</hi> denied, and diſallowed it: becauſe neither <hi>a Wife</hi> being under Covert bond, nor <hi>a Child,</hi> being under tuition, are <hi>ſui juris.</hi> They have not power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their own ſelves. The <hi>Wife hath not power over her ſelf, but the Husband:</hi> ſo nor hath the <hi>Child,</hi> but the <hi>Father:</hi> and conſequently neither have they power over their own Actions and engagements; but he, under whoſe power themſelves are. We know a Bond of a wife, or child under age ſignifies no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, nor can they be ſued, they have no obligation in the Courts of men. There is proportionably the ſame reaſon of <hi>Publick Oaths,</hi> which are the Bonds of People who are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Government, or Tuition of their Prince. If <hi>People en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into an Oath,</hi> and bind themſelves to an Action; and the <hi>King,</hi> under whoſe charge they are, who is <hi>Pater Patriae,</hi> and whom they are bound to obey, ſhall <hi>diſallow thoſe Oaths,</hi> and <hi>forbid thoſe Actions;</hi> they may have reaſon to ask God forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for their <hi>Raſh engagements,</hi> but are not obliged to do that which they have ſworne: the things being not legally in their power, becauſe of a Superior Authority, that diſallows them, to which they<note n="(n)" place="margin">Rom. 13.5</note> 
                        <hi>muſt be ſubject.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Thoſe oaths,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>34.</hi>
                        </note> which in the matter of them are againſt that moſt neceſſary condition of all oaths, <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> never did, nor can oblige, <hi>(i.e.)</hi> if the thing ſworne
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51074:11"/>to, or Promiſed by Oath, be diſhoneſt, unjuſt, impious; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Law of God, Moral equity, the right of a third Perſon, &amp;c. it may at no hand be done. There can be no juſtice, and conſequently no obligation to <hi>worſhip an Idol,</hi> to <hi>Kill, Steale, Ribell,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>justice</hi> requires that all lawful and poſſible engagements be performed, but ſinful and unjuſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations retracted. That Advice is certainly ſound, which a <hi>Reverend Author</hi> gives.<note n="(o)" place="margin">In malis promiſſis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcinde fidem; in turpi voto muta decretum; quod incautè voviſti n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>cias; impia enim promiſſio, quae ſcelere ad impl. tur. <hi>Glouc.</hi> on <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tech.</hi> out of <hi>Iſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>In wicked Promiſes, reſcind thy faith; in a diſhonest Vow change the aecree; do not that which thou haſt vowed unwarily; it is an impi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                              <desc>••…</desc>
                           </gap> oath which cannot be made good but by wickedneſs.</hi> It is a moſt ſure rule, <hi>Juramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum pietatis non debet eſſe vinculum ixiquitatis,</hi> for otherwiſe <hi>Scolus eſſet ſides.</hi> Such was the oath of<note n="(p)" place="margin">Matth. 14.7-12.</note> 
                        <hi>Herod</hi> to <hi>Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias,</hi> an oath <hi>ſinfully taken, and wickedly kept.</hi> Such was that oath of <hi>David,</hi> He ſwore,<note n="(q)" place="margin">1 Sam. 25.21, 22, 34.</note> with an imprecation of a <hi>Curſe</hi> upon himſelf to <hi>Deſtroy Nabal</hi> and <hi>all his houſe,</hi> which yet upon the petition of <hi>Abigail</hi> he <hi>piouſly broke,</hi> but ſhould <hi>ſinfully have performed.</hi> Such was the Raſh Oath of <hi>Saul,</hi>
                        <note n="(r)" place="margin">1 Sam. 14.24, 44, 45.</note> which would have engaged him to murther <hi>Jonathan;</hi> but the People prevented, what he ſhould <hi>ſinfully have done.</hi> Such was the<note n="(s)" place="margin">Act. 23.12, 21.</note> Oath of thoſe <hi>forty Jews</hi> to <hi>kill Paul,</hi> which they <hi>wickedly ſwore,</hi> and ſhould more <hi>wickedly have committed.</hi> In this caſe, it matters not <hi>how, when,</hi> or <hi>by what means, we were brought to ſwear,</hi> ſo much, as <hi>what we have ſworne. Oaths</hi> engaging to <hi>unlawful,</hi> and <hi>unjuſt</hi> Actions, (though through ignorance, error, weakneſs, miſpriſion, ſurreption, fear, or malice entred into) are <hi>not to be kept,</hi> nor have any obligation upon the Conſcience: They engage the Swearer to repent of, and retract his Oaths, but not at all to performe them.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The truth is,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>35.</hi>
               </note> to keep ſuch an Oath is a <hi>double ſin. A ſin</hi> it was <hi>to ſwear;</hi> and another ſin, to <hi>perform the oath; Quod malè juratur pejus ſervatur.</hi> For, what God hath forbidden, he will nor have done at any hand. He hath forbidden us <hi>to ſwear</hi> or <hi>promiſe them,</hi> but much more <hi>to do them,</hi> and to keep ſuch Oaths, is but to adde ſin to ſin. Were the Oath <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted by fear;</hi> it is <hi>our ſin to he affrighted into ſin,</hi> who ſhould rather <hi>chooſe to die, than ſin.</hi> We muſt beg pardon for our baſe fears, but at no hand adde another ſin in performance:
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51074:11"/>and the ſame muſt we conclude of <hi>Surpriſe,</hi> or <hi>Paſſion,</hi> when the matter is unjuſt or ſinful. Memorable is the Story which <hi>Munſter</hi>
               <note n="(t)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Munſt.</hi> de Germ. l. 3. c. 499.</note> records of <hi>Jutha</hi> the Daughter of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Otho.</hi> 2. <q>She was by the Emperour, her Father, put into a <hi>Nunnery;</hi> but by force taken thence by <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>dalric,</hi> or <hi>Ulderick</hi> the Son of the <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Duke of Bohemia,</hi> and married to him. The Emperour, urged by the indignity of the fact, ſwears to revenge himſelf upon <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lderick;</hi> and to lead an Army into <hi>Bohemia.</hi> He doth ſo, His and <hi>Ulde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks</hi> Armies meet. <hi>Jutha</hi> the Daughter of the one, and Wife of the other, aſtoniſhed, and affrighted, haſtily runs to her Father, begs to ſpeak with him before the Armies joyn, or he lets his fury rage in blood. She obtains this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and ſues for Peace and Reconcilement. The <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour</hi> urgeth <hi>his oath,</hi> whereby he had bound himſelf: She anſwers,<note n="(v)" place="margin">Vana eſt religio quae ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leri locum fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit; vim crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta non ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt. <hi>Munſt,</hi> ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>That Religion is vain, which makes way to wickedneſs; nor can any oath give force, power or licence, to a crime, or ſin.</hi> Thus ſhe ſatisfies her fathers ſcruple, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains her ſuit.</q>
            </p>
            <p>So that No Oath can oblige us either 1. <hi>Againſt Piety,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note> the duties of the firſt Table. Or, 2. <hi>Againſt Juſtice and Charity,</hi> the duties of the ſecond. For theſe are the matters of the<note n="(u)" place="margin">Jam. 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>Royal Law</hi> of God, and indiſpenſible duties up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on man: And in vain ſhould the Lord of heaven give us ſuch a Law, if we might at pleaſure ſwear, and then upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of ſuch an Oath be at liberty to break ſuch a Law, the <hi>leaſt Commandments</hi>
               <note n="(x)" place="margin">Mat. 5.17, 18, 19.</note> whereof God at no hand will have to be broken. But particularly, ſo far as refers to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent purpoſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>No Oath</hi> can oblige us againſt equity,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>37.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>againſt the right of a third perſon,</hi> or to the <hi>direct injury of our Neighbour.</hi> For, though having ſworne to our own inconvenience, we muſt not change, becauſe we are Maſters of our own rights, and may, if we pleaſe, give them away: yet of anothers rights we are not. God hath bound us by his Law to preſerve them, and we may not ſwear to deſtroy them; nor may we deſtroy them, though we have ſworne ſo.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>No Oath</hi> can oblige us againſt the Duty,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>38.</hi>
                  </note> that we owe to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51074:12"/>our Govèrnours or Superiours, or the Laws that we do and muſt live under. God hath bound us to <hi>Obedience,</hi> and no oath can oblige to <hi>Rebellion, Sedition, Schiſm,</hi> or <hi>Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence:</hi> no more than the<note n="(y)" place="margin">Mat. 15.5. Mark 7.11, 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Corban,</hi> or pretence of a <hi>vow</hi> and a <hi>dedication of all to God,</hi> could free the <hi>Jews</hi> from yielding that <hi>honour, obedience, and maintenance,</hi> which God had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged them to yield to their <hi>Parents.</hi> He that well underſtands the Fifth Commandment, <hi>Honour thy Father, and Mother,</hi> knows that no Oath can oblige a man to riſe up againſt them, and turn his <hi>Father</hi> out of doors, yea or deny the duty which he owes to them: and as little can it oblige us to endeavour to <hi>Subvert the Government,</hi> or <hi>overthrow thoſe Governours</hi> in Church or State, to whom, by vertue of the ſame Precept, we are obliged to be<note n="(z)" place="margin">Rom. 13.1-5. 1 Pet 2.13, 14. <hi>Sect.</hi> 39.</note> 
                  <hi>ſubject, not only for wrath, but for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience-ſake.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. Nor can <hi>any oath</hi> oblige us againſt the former juſt obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations upon us; nor againſt thoſe lawful Oaths, which we had formerly taken, and are not yet free from. <hi>Prior obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatio postoriori praejudicat.</hi> A former obligation doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judge, and prevent the latter. For every lawful Oath having an unqueſtionable tie upon the conſcience, it muſt be both un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful to ſwear any thing contrary to it, and though we ſwear, we cannot be obliged. For we cannot be bound to <hi>forſwear;</hi> yea, we are infallibly bound,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Exod. 20.7. Mat. 5.33.</note> 
                  <hi>not to forſwear our ſelves.</hi> A latter Oath cannot oblige, when the very <hi>taking</hi> of it, is an <hi>act of perjury,</hi> and the <hi>keeping of it would be a perſiſting in the perjury,</hi> in the breach of our former Oaths. This had the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Vid. <hi>Simſ. Chron. Cath.</hi> Part. 1. am. 3480.</note> 
                  <hi>Phaenician Navi</hi> learned, who in the ſervice of <hi>Cambyſes</hi> were commanded by him to ſail againſt <hi>Carthage;</hi> though they were under his pay, and probably bound by the <hi>Souldiers Oath,</hi> the <hi>Sacramentum Militia</hi> (and the Souldier is bound to obey, not diſpute his <hi>Generals</hi> commands) yet they thought themſelves not obliged in this, but denied obedience, becauſe they were <hi>by a former Oath obliged to the Carthaginians:</hi> and they therefore thought, that their latter Obligation to <hi>Cambyies</hi> could not oblige them to deſtroy thoſe, whom by a former Oath they were bound to protect and aſſiſt. An Oath, that is <hi>unlawfully</hi> entred into, becauſe <hi>Raſhly,</hi> may yet bind,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51074:12"/>when the <hi>matter is honeſt,</hi> and <hi>in our power:</hi> but No Oath, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful in the matter of it, can either be <hi>lawfully taken,</hi> or when taken, <hi>can lay any obligation;</hi> for <hi>No Oath can oblig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> us to ſin.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>We have now ſeen the general caſes concerning the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>40.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Qualities, Obligation,</hi> and <hi>Non-obligation of an Oath.</hi> It will not now be difficult to ſhew, by applying theſe general things to the particular caſe of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> the <hi>Non-obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,</hi> and <hi>Unlawfulneſs of that Oath.</hi> I have been very ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in examining and conſidering this caſe, not, <hi>Whether the Penalty in this Act of Parliament be too ſevere</hi> (for into that we have no call to inquire) but, whether <hi>We may lawfully do as that Act requires,</hi> and make that <hi>Acknowledgement</hi> which this Law enjoyns us. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iz. Whether this Covenant were lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken, or may lawfully be kept:</hi> and <hi>whether yet it ſo obligeth, that we may not renounce it, and declare as much.</hi> And upon theſe premiſed principles I judge we may be fully convinced of its <hi>Illegality,</hi> and <hi>Non-obligation,</hi> and conſequently may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully <hi>acknowledge</hi> and ſubſcribe ſo.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. It will not be denied, for it is unqueſtionable,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>41.</hi>
                  </note> that <hi>This Covenant was a Publick Oath;</hi> and then according to the former rule, it may alſo be <hi>annulled, revoked,</hi> and <hi>abrogated by a Publick Authority,</hi> Suppoſe the <hi>Authority</hi> were <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme</hi> that required it; ſuppoſe, that we <hi>in obedience to that Authority did lawfully ſwear it:</hi> yet without diſpute, the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, that is infallibly Supreme</hi> with us, <hi>doth now Revoke,</hi> and hath <hi>diſannulled</hi> it. And here is evidently then <hi>Ceſſatio materiae,</hi> and ſuch a <hi>Notable Alteration of the state of things referring to the Principal matter,</hi> which had it then been, this Oath would neither have been impoſed nor ſworne; and we may juſtly conclude, that, if it ever did oblige, yet now it doth not: unleſs we can be obliged to maintain a Law, which an <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> hath repealed. But this is not all, for this ſuppoſeth it eſtabliſhed by a Law. But</item>
               <item>2. It was an Oath <hi>Impoſed by thoſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>42.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>who had no authority to impoſe an Oaeth.</hi> It was a <hi>Covenant</hi> entred into by <hi>Subjects;</hi> and <hi>diſallowed by the King,</hi> who then ruled over us: and now again, by <hi>His preſent Majeſty,</hi> with the full conſent of <hi>all
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51074:13"/>the estates of the Kingdom in Parliament,</hi> abrogated: and therefore cannot have an obligation, in analogy to, and by vertue of that Law of God before mentioned, <hi>Numb.</hi> 30. for in this caſe there is the ſame reaſon of <hi>Subjects under Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as of <hi>Children under tuition,</hi> or a <hi>Wife under Covert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bond.</hi> We had no power to enter into ſuch an <hi>Oath</hi> or <hi>Combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation;</hi> nor, it being denied, and diſallowed by our <hi>Soveraign,</hi> can we be obliged by it: for this muſt be ſtill ſuppoſed a tacite condition, <hi>That our Governours, and the Laws that we are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, will allow and permit it.</hi> But more,</item>
               <item>3.<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>43.</hi>
                  </note> It was an Oath <hi>Unlawfully ſworne, and cannot but be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully kept.</hi> And the unlawfulneſs will appear in theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>1. It was <hi>Unlawful in the Impoſition:</hi> as being impoſed by <hi>no lawful Authority.</hi> The Laws of this Kingdom acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge nothing to have the force and power of a Law, but from the ſtamp of the <hi>Royal Authority,</hi> the Kings <hi>Fiat:</hi> which that <hi>Ordinance,</hi> which impoſed this <hi>Covenant,</hi> never had. It muſt therefore be concluded to be <hi>impoſed upon the Subjects of this Realm, contrary to the Known Laws and Liberties of this Kingdom:</hi> a thing, even the ſame, which thoſe two Houſes of P. which impoſed this Oath, declared; when they took away and annulled the late <hi>Canons,</hi> and that Oath, which was ſo Decried for the, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> viz.<note n="*" place="margin">Exact. Coll. p. 859, 860.</note> That <hi>A New Oath cannot be impoſed without an Act of Parliament;</hi> which this was never eſtabliſhed by.</item>
               <item>2.<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>44.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful in the Ends of it.</hi> Which (whatſoever, and how ſpecious ſoever the Pretences were) have appeared ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently to the world to have been indeed <hi>Seditious,</hi> and <hi>Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</hi> The charge may ſeem high, and too uncharitable: but let it be remembred, (and it is too evident then to be denied) This very <hi>Covenant</hi> was made the main Engine of a deſign, the ſaddeſt, the bittereſt, that <hi>England</hi> ever ſaw before, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage a people againſt the Church and State: and to Bring in the <hi>Scots</hi> to aſſiſt them in a diſmal <hi>War againſt the King;</hi> which they would not be brought to do, till <hi>this Kingdom</hi> did <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> to throw out her <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and extirpate the eſtabliſhed <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy, Root and Branch.</hi> So that the great ends aimed at
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51074:13"/>in the contriving and exacting this Covenant to be ſworne, was, 1. Not to Reform ſome abuſes, or, to take away ſome needleſs Officers, or, prevent ſome irregular proceedings in the Courts: but utterly to <hi>aboliſh the eſtabliſhed Government in the Church.</hi> And then, 2. By the Aſſiſtance of the <hi>Scots</hi> to maintain a War againſt the <hi>King,</hi> and to reduce Him to ſuch Terms as the Two Houſes ſhould think fit to put upon Him: That they might be able to <hi>Give Laws</hi> to the <hi>King,</hi> from whom they were bound to <hi>Receive them.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Unlawful</hi> alſo it was in the <hi>Matter of it,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>45.</hi>
                  </note> as binding men
<list>
                     <item>1. To <hi>Impoſſibilities,</hi> if not <hi>in nature,</hi> yet certainly <hi>in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iz.</hi> binding men to do that, which they had <hi>no power, no authority to do.</hi> What <hi>Power</hi> or authority had <hi>Subjects</hi> to enter into ſuch an Oath, not only <hi>without,</hi> but <hi>contrary to</hi> the mind, conſent, and expreſs Command and Will of their <hi>Soverargn?</hi> What <hi>Authority, P. e,</hi> or <hi>Call</hi> had they, to endeavour the Overthrowing of that Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as <hi>Antichristian,</hi> under which the <hi>Chriſtian Church</hi> had been happy, and flouriſhed ſo many hundred years; and which they were by the poſitive Laws of our Land bound not to oppoſe, but to obey and ſubmit unto? <hi>Id ſolum poſſumus, quod jure poſſumus,</hi> Properly, <hi>we only can do that, which we lawfully may do.</hi> In this ſenſe then, the <hi>Covenant</hi> ſhould bind to <hi>impoſſibilities;</hi> which argues a <hi>Nullity:</hi> unleſs <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects</hi> can pretend to a <hi>power</hi> to overthrow any thing which the Law eſtabliſheth, whenſoever they like it not. Farther,</item>
                     <item>2. Unlawful it was, as binding to <hi>Unjuſt,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>46.</hi>
                        </note> and <hi>Diſhoneſt things</hi> alſo.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Infallibly, No Oath can bind to Sedition, or, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow of thoſe Laws that we are bound to obey: and that Oath obligeth to <hi>injuſtice</hi> and <hi>impiety,</hi> which obligeth to <hi>Perjury,</hi> and <hi>the breach of former, not yet cancelled, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations.</hi> Now the <hi>Laws</hi> had eſtabliſhed <hi>Epiſcopacy; Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> had <hi>Sworne Obedience to the Biſhop.</hi> There can there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be <hi>no obligation,</hi> becauſe ſo much <hi>Impiety</hi> in that Oath, which if it ſhould oblige, would oblige to <hi>Perjury.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:51074:14"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> I know what hath been ſaid to this, Viz. <hi>That, thoſe who have Sworne obedience to the Laws of the Land, are not thereby prohibited to endeavour by all lawful means the abolition of thoſe Laws, when they prove inconvenient or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, 1.<note place="margin">Solut. 1.</note> The Utmoſt of that <hi>Obedience,</hi> which was ſworn to the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> was but <hi>in Licitis &amp; Honestis,</hi> in lawful and honeſt things. And how a lawful and honeſt obedience ſhould be culpable; or the <hi>Laws</hi> that required it, ſhould be <hi>miſchievous,</hi> or, <hi>inconvenient,</hi> I confeſs I yet never could have eyes to ſee; nor (I think) any man elſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">Sol. 2.</note> Had the <hi>Laws,</hi> which eſtabliſhed <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> been ſuch: yet it will ſeem very ſtrange to a conſidering, and intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent man, that, preſently to enter into ſuch a <hi>Covenant</hi> and Combination; and by force and power to break through thoſe Laws, and overthrow the eſtabliſhed Government, <hi>whether the King will or no,</hi> ſhould ever be accounted a <hi>lawful means.</hi> Again,</p>
            <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">Sol. 3.</note> Suppoſe it <hi>inconvenient,</hi> yet <hi>Subjects</hi> have no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to <hi>Make a Law,</hi> or <hi>Alter a Law for themſelves.</hi> If any <hi>miſchief,</hi> or <hi>inconvenience</hi> had been in that Law; or the Government eſtabliſhed; we might lawfully have <hi>ſhewed the Grievances,</hi> and <hi>Petitioned</hi> for a redreſs to thoſe, to whom only it belonged to reform them: but to Swear to extirpate a Government, to overthrow a Law, againſt the Law-givers conſent; this is ſomewhat elſe than a peaceable petition, or an honeſt endeavour. Though we might by humble petition in ſuch a caſe beg a Reformation, yet without all controverſie we were bound by our <hi>Allegiance, Duty,</hi> and <hi>former oaths,</hi> to <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey</hi> that which was eſtabliſhed, until the Supreme power ſhould ſee it juſt or fit to alter it.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>47.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That Oath</hi> which bindeth men to the <hi>injury</hi> of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>whom we are bound to love as we love our ſelves,</hi> and <hi>to do to them, as we would have others do to us,</hi> is <hi>unjuſt in the matter of it,</hi> and conſequently <hi>unlawful,</hi> and bindeth not: But this <hi>Covenant</hi> bindeth to ſuch an <hi>injury;</hi> an injury, not of one, or two, but an whole <hi>Order of Biſhops</hi> who were once a <hi>Third Eſtate</hi> (and by the good Providence
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51074:14"/>of God are ſo now again) to the depriving of them both of their Places, and Power in the Church; and of their Lands, Eſtates and Livelihoods, that if they lived, they muſt live up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Alms; as many in the late Confuſions were even forced to do.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It was infallibly unjuſt, and diſhoneſt, and wicked, to endeavour and conſpire the <hi>deſtruction of innocent, faithful, loyal ſubjects;</hi> to ſwear the death, confiſcation of goods of all thoſe, that conſcientiouſly thought themſelves bound, (as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they were) by their <hi>Allegiance</hi> to ſerve and aſſiſt the King, and to preſerve him from that fatal end, to which this <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> (though, I verily believe, many of thoſe, who ſometimes were zealous in impoſing it, and thouſands that took it, never intended ſuch a thing) did make and prepare too ſad a way. Yet this do they ſwear, <hi>viz.</hi> to diſcover all ſuch, as <hi>have been, or ſhall be Malignants</hi>—and to <hi>bring them to publick trial, that they may receive condign puniſhment.</hi> And who theſe <hi>Malignants</hi> were, what the <hi>condign puniſhment was,</hi> is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently declared by thoſe who impoſed the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by their avowed ſenſe and publick Declaration, it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt whom men were by this <hi>Covenant</hi> bound to perſecute and deſtroy.<note n="*" place="margin">See, Exact. Coll. p. 260, 576, 509.</note> 
               <hi>All perſons, who, upon any pretence whatſoever did aſſiſt His Majeſty with Horſe, Armes, Plate or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in that war,</hi> theſe were declared <hi>Traytors, unparallel'd Traytors, and who ought to ſuffer as Traytors</hi> (and what the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of ſuch is, we need not be told) and to theſe was vowed <hi>speedy, and exemplary puniſhment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many other particulars might be produced to prove the <hi>Non-obligation,</hi> and the <hi>unlawfulneſſe of that Covenant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>48.</hi>
               </note> but theſe are enough to engage us to acknowledge, and to juſtifie us in ſuch an <hi>acknowledgment</hi> as the preſent Law, the <hi>Act for Uniformity</hi> requires. Some, perhaps, may not be convinced of the truth of all theſe particulars here aſſerted: yet, me thinks, we may eaſily ſee enough to ſatisfie our ſouls, as to all that this <hi>Act</hi> requireth of us. And really, <hi>the Act</hi> in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ſeemes to be penned with ſuch <hi>Caution, Prudence,</hi> and <hi>Tenderneſs,</hi> that no conſcientious Chriſtian may be enſnar'd by ſuch a ſubſcription, nor have any occaſion juſtly to ſcruple ſuch an Acknowledgment. For,</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:51074:15"/>
            <p n="1">1. As to the <hi>Obligation,</hi> it requires us only to acknowledge its <hi>preſent</hi> non-obligation. Not, that it never did, but that it <hi>doth not now oblige.</hi> Many perhaps may think that they were obliged, while that power ſtood, when yet they may now ſee they are not. But whatſoever was the Obligation, whether ever it did, or did not bind, all that we now are to declare, is, That there <hi>now lies to Obligation on us or any other by this oath to endeavor the alteration of Government in Church or State.</hi> Let me ſeriouſly put the queſtion to thoſe that yet make ſcruple, and are afraid to ſubſcribe: Yea, let all loyal and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hearted Chriſtians put the queſtion to their own ſouls, and as in the preſence of the eternal, All-ſeeing, and moſt righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God, give anſwer to themſelves.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1.<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>50.</hi>
                  </note> Can any Oath, that we have raſhly taken, oblige any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to reſiſt, or endeavour to root out a Government, which the Law hath eſtabliſhed, and doth ſtill maintain, and require obedience to? then, certainly, diſobedience and rebellion could be no ſin; nor any Government be firme, or Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours ſecure, when men that like it not ſhall by Oath bind themſelves not to obey, but aboliſh it. Prelacy is reſtored, and by an unqueſtionable Law eſtabliſhed, do ye really think in your conſciences that ye are now bound to extirpate it? not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſome of the <hi>ſubordinate officers</hi> (as ſome, who in the ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of their hearts were drawn in to ſwear this <hi>Covenant,</hi> did think they only were obliged againſt the whole frame, as ſo compounded together, and if any alteration were made, though but in ſome of the loweſt Officers, were it but the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval of ſome <hi>Officials, Comiſſaries, &amp;c.</hi> they had ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwered their obligation,) But even the <hi>Biſhops</hi> themſelves, (for whatſoever ſome might think when they took the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> the <hi>Impoſers</hi> of it, by their actions ſhewed, that they meant not the laying aſide only <hi>ſome Officers</hi> not ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, nor of Divine inſtitution, but the whole <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and the very <hi>Biſhops</hi> as <hi>a plant not of Gods planting.</hi>) Yea, if occaſion and opportunity ſhould be offered, may not ſome up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame pretence riſe up againſt the whole Miniſtery, and from the <hi>ſame Covenant</hi> plead the extirpation of all the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> alſo, becauſe they are made ſo by <hi>Epiſcopal Ordination,</hi> as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51074:15"/>ſuch who are, and muſt be included under the title of <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Officers depending on that Hierarchy,</hi> which in the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> men with the <hi>Hierarchy</hi> bind themſelves to <hi>exterpate?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Do ye really think, that,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>51.</hi>
                  </note> notwithſtanding it is enacted by a Law that to <hi>raiſe and bear armes against the King</hi> (though by <hi>order</hi> or <hi>ordinance</hi> of <hi>both</hi> or <hi>either houſe of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi>) is <hi>Treaſon,</hi> yet that you are bound ſtill to maintaine Armies againſt <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> if he will not conſent to the matters ſworn to in the <hi>Covenant:</hi> and to <hi>aſſist each other, and never by any terror, fear, or perſwaſion be drawn from ſuch a combination?</hi> for ſo runs the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and if ſuch be mens principles, that it ſtill obligeth, how can our peace, or Laws, or Government ever be ſecure?</item>
               <item>3. Do ye really think,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>52.</hi>
                  </note> that you are ſtill obliged to bring all that did adhere to, and aſſiſt <hi>His Majeſty</hi> in the late warre, to puniſhment; to ſuffer as <hi>Malignants, Traytors, unparallel'd Traytors,</hi> (as they were then called, and the <hi>Covenant</hi> meant)? If the <hi>Covenant</hi> have any obligation, it muſt oblige to theſe things, for ſo is it there <hi>in terminis</hi> expreſſely ſworn. Let me beſeech all, ſoberly to lay their hands upon their hearts, and anſwer theſe queſtions to their own ſouls, and if they are not obliged in theſe (as beyond all doubt they are not, yea beyond all controverſie they are tied by all obligations to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) then muſt we conclude that it is truth, which by this <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> we are obliged to <hi>declare,</hi> and we may lawfully (and conſequently, being ſo legally commanded, we are in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence bound to) <hi>acknowledge</hi> and ſubſcribe, that whether ever there were or were not any obligation by the <hi>Covenant,</hi> yet now, <hi>There lieth no obligation upon us, or any other perſon by his Oath, to endeavor any change or alteration of Government ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Church or State.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe conſiderations are ſufficient to ſatisfie us then as to the firſt part or propoſition to be acknowledged concerning the Covenant, <hi>viz.</hi> its preſent <hi>non-obligation.</hi> Which is no more,<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>53.</hi>
               </note> than that, 1. What ever it did heretofore, yet <hi>now</hi> it doth not oblige, being taken away by a Law of a Publick and juſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. And, 2. However, man may yet be obliged to ſome other things therein mentioned, as to endeavour <hi>in our places
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51074:16"/>and callings, the extirpation of Hereſie, Schiſm and Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and whatſoever is contrary to ſound Doctrine, and the power of Godlineſs: to maintain and defend the Kings Majeſties per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and authority</hi> (without that Reſtriction there annext, our <hi>Allegiance</hi> being due to Him, not as He is a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> or <hi>Godly,</hi> but as He is <hi>our King;</hi>) <hi>and to amend our lives, and go before each other in the example of a real reformation,</hi> &amp;c. Though, I ſay, we may be, and are ſtill obliged to all theſe things (yet, I think, not from this Covenant, but from other grounds and principles of more unqueſtionable authority) yet we may make that acknowledgement as the <hi>Act</hi> requires, which is not, that there <hi>lies no obligation by the Covenant to endeavour theſe things:</hi> but only <hi>No obligation to endeavour the alteration of the Government in Church or State: (i.e.)</hi> No obligation to Sedition, Rebellion, or, Oppoſition of the Laws which God hath commanded us to live under.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">Sect. <hi>54.</hi>
               </note> As to the latter part to be declared, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Unlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of that Covenant,</hi> it is only, that <hi>it was an Unlawful Oath,</hi> and though there may be many things to prove it ſo, yet we are there required to acknowledge but this one, <hi>The impoſition of it contrary to the known Laws and Liberties of this Kingdom,</hi> which muſt be acknowledged by thoſe, who themſelves have declared, that <hi>No new Oath can be impoſed but by Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> which this never had, as before was ſhewn. Is it not undoubtedly true, that there can be no <hi>Act of Parliament,</hi> no Law, without the <hi>Royal aſſent?</hi> and was not this impoſed without, yea contrary to the Conſent of <hi>His late Majesty</hi> then Reigning? Diſallowed ſtill, condemned and revoked now by <hi>His preſent Majesty?</hi> yea condemned and diſannul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by a Law of <hi>England,</hi> an <hi>Act of Parliament?</hi> So that it is moſt certain, that, <hi>It was an Unlawful Oath,</hi> ſo far at leaſt as concerns the manner of the impoſition, and the authority of the Impoſers, as, <hi>Impoſed upon the Subjects of this Realm againſt the known Laws and Liberties of this Kingdom.</hi> And this is all that we are here required to acknowledge.</p>
            <p>Let me but adde the determination of the <hi>Aſſembly of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines</hi> then called together by the two Houſes of Parl. and ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>55.</hi>
               </note> in their <hi>Exhortation</hi> an next to that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51074:16"/>In anſwer to that Plea of the Clergy, who might ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, [<hi>They were ſworne to obey the Biſhops</hi> in Licitis &amp; Honeſtis, <hi>and therefore could not take this Oath to extirpate them</hi>—] They conclude thus — <hi>If there ſhould be yet any Oath found into which any Miniſters or others have entred, not warranted by the Laws of God and the Land, in this caſe they muſt tell them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and others, that ſuch Oaths call for Repentance, and not Pertinacy in them.</hi> Now, are there not many things in this Oath againſt the Laws of God? is it not wholly againſt the Laws of the Land? Where do the Laws of God or the Land warrant Subjects to <hi>extirpate</hi> an eſtabliſhed Order and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, without the conſent, yea againſt the mind of their Soveraign? Where do the Laws of God or the Land warrant any to proſecute thoſe who according to their duty and Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, ſerve, and labour to defend the Life, the Perſon, the Authority of the King, and act by His Commiſſion, as Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants, and evil Inſtruments, and to puniſh them as Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours? Sure I am, it was an Oath, much more <hi>againſt the Laws of God and the Land,</hi> than any of thoſe Oaths, wherein the Subjects of this Realm were before engaged, whether the <hi>Oaths of Supremacy</hi> and <hi>Allegiance;</hi> or, the Oath of <hi>Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical obedience to the Biſhops,</hi> (which are warranted by both;) can with any ſhadow of reaſon be pretended to be. <hi>This Oath</hi> therefore, even according to their determination, <hi>calls for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and not Pertinacy in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, really, <hi>Repentance,</hi> earneſt,<note place="margin">Sest. <hi>56.</hi>
               </note> unfained Repentance it doth call for. We may too juſtly lament, and take up the words of the Prophet, <hi>Becauſe of Swearing, the Land mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</hi> The Land hath mourned, under the Scourges of God, and we have yet cauſe to fear, leſt God again make us feel the ſmart of his Rods; Sure I am we have yet reaſon to <hi>mourn,</hi> in ſorrrow and compunction of heart, for the <hi>ſins of our Oaths,</hi> (beſides thoſe cuſtomary, prophane, <hi>Tavern,</hi> and <hi>street-oaths</hi> of ungodly men,) for our neglect and breach of thoſe Sacred ties of <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy,</hi> which we had ſworne, and violated; for thoſe many unlawful Oaths and Engagements, which were too raſhly entred into, and more ſinfully kept. O let us with tears in our eyes, and contrition in our hearts, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51074:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>beg pardon of our God, whoſe name in theſe we have ſo often taken in vain; and teſtifie the ſincerity of our Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance by a Conſcientious returning to our duty, in the care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful practice of the ſtricteſt Piety to God; unſtained and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Faith and Allegiance to the King our Soveraign; and a chearful and ready obedience to the Laws upon us both in Church and State.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt now (Reader) my thoughts concerning this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement that we are to make of the <hi>Non-obligation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sect. <hi>57.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Unlawfulneſs of the Covenant.</hi> A I my deſign is <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> and to offer what I am able, to remove thoſe doubts and ſtumbling-blocks that lie in the way, and hinder both. For thoſe ſober, humble, and conſcientious men, who yet dare not renounce that Coven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt, which though unadviſedly ſworne, they yet think to oblige, and are therefore afraid to ſubſcribe this <hi>Declaration</hi> preſcribed, I ſhall preſume to hope, they may find ſomething in theſe papers, that may ſatisfie their doubts, remove their fears, and convince them of their real duty, that by their groundleſs ſcruples they may not make themſelves uncapable of ſerving <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Church in the Publick ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of their Functions and Miniſteries. Read, Ponder, and Conſider the matters before thee, lay aſide all paſſion and prejudice, and the by-thoughts of a vain reputation: let not men that have erred, be aſhamed to confeſs it, but be more aſhamed to perſiſt in it. Repentance is the next Door to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency. <hi>Quem paenitet peccâſſe paenè eſt innocens.</hi> We have ſuffered a ſad ſhipwrack by our Follies and Sins, Repentance is <hi>Secunda tabula, poſt naufragium,</hi> a Planck left, by means whereof, through Gods mercy, we may yet get ſafe to ſhore, and be happy again.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Si quid noviſti rectius iſtis,</l>
               <l>Candidus imparti: ſi non, his utere mecum.</l>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
